<manpage package="dbi" title="dbi_sqlite" id="dbi_sqlite" cat="dbi">
<namesection>
<name>dbi_sqlite3</name>
<desc>create dbi object for accessing sqlite3 databases</desc>
</namesection>

<synopsis>
<syntax><cmd>dbi_interface</cmd> ?<m>objectName</m>?</syntax>
</synopsis>

<section>
<title>DESCRIPTION</title>

<p>
The <cmd>dbi_sqlite</cmd> command creates an object <m>objectName</m> that
can be used to connect to sqlite databases using its native API. If
<m>objectName</m> is not provided, a name will be automatically generated
and returned by the command The object created supports the <ref
manpage="interface_dbi">dbi interface</ref> for accessing and querying
databases.
</p>

<p>
The object supports transactions, lines, serials, views and checks.
Foreign keys are accepted, but not checked sqlite3 dbi objects do not
support column permissions, roles, domains or permissions, as these are
not supported by sqlite3.
</p>

<section>
<title>Extra commands supported</title>
<commandlist>

<commanddef>
<command><cmd>objectName</cmd> <method>function</method> <m>name</m> <m>script</m></command>
<desc>Create an Sqlite function with name <m>name</m>. <m>script</m> will be executed
when the function is called (with parameters apended to it). 
</desc>
</commanddef>

<commanddef>
<command><cmd>objectName</cmd> <method>collate</method> <m>name</m> <m>script</m></command>
<desc>Create a new Sqlite collation with name <m>name</m>. <m>script</m> will be executed
when the collation is used with to strings as parameters. The application defined collation 
routine should return negative, zero or positive if the first string is less than, equal to, 
or greater than the second string
</desc>
</commanddef>

</commandlist>
</section>

<section>
<title>Extra collations</title>
The dbi interface also adds two new collations:
<dl>
<dt>DICT</dt><dd>dictionary sort: Sort alphabetically, but numbers are treated as integers:
e.g. test2 wil be sorted before test10</dd>
<dt>DICTREAL</dt><dd>dictionary sort: Sort alphabetically, but numbers are treated as reals:
e.g. a2.0555 wil be sorted before a2.08.</dd>
</dl>
</section>

<section>
<title>Extra functions</title>
The dbi interface also adds two new functions to sqlite:
<dl>
<dt>regexp</dt><dd>This function has to parameters: the pattern and the value. Thus allows the 
use of regular expressions in queries, e.g.: where "first_name" regexp '^[Jj]o'</dd>
<dt>list_concat</dt><dd>This aggregate function returns a proper list of all elements in the query</dd>
</dl>
</section>

<seealso>
<ref>interface_dbi</ref>
<ref>interface_dbi_admin</ref>
</seealso>

<keywords>
<keyword>dbi</keyword>
<keyword>sqlite</keyword>
<keyword>sqlite3</keyword>
<keyword>interface</keyword>
<keyword>database</keyword>
<keyword>sql</keyword>
</keywords>

</manpage>

